<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Zhang Tao lab</title>
    <description>Bioinformatics, Epigenetics and Genomics.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 11:29:04 +0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 11:29:04 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Splicing-mediated activation of SHAGGY-like kinases underpinning carbon partitioning in Arabidopsis seeds</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Glycogen synthase kinase 3 (GSK3) family members serve as signaling hubs for plant development and stress responses, yet the underlying mechanism of their transcriptional regulation remains a long-standing mystery. Here we show that the tran- scription of SHAGGY-like kinase 11/12 (SK11/12), two members of the GSK3 gene family, is promoted by the splicing factor SmD1b, which is essential for distributing carbon sources into storage and protective components in Arabidopsis seeds. The chromatin recruitment of SmD1b at the SK11/12 loci promotes their transcription associated with co-transcriptional splicing of the first introns in the 50-untranslated region of SK11/12. The loss of SmD1b function generates transcripts with unspliced introns that create disruptive R-loops to hamper the transcriptional elongation of SK11/12, in addition to compromising the recruitment of RNA polymerase II to the SK11/12 genomic regions. These effects imposed by SmD1b de- termine the transcription of SK11/12 to confer a key switch of carbon flow among metabolic pathways in zygotic and ma- ternal tissues in seeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-the-plant-cell-2022&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/plcell/advance-article-abstract/doi/10.1093/plcell/koac110/6569842?redirectedFrom=fulltext&quot;&gt;the Plant Cell (2022)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;``&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/06/14/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/06/14/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Role of lncRNAs in cis- and trans-regulatory responses to salt in Populus trichocarpa</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs) are emerging as versatile regulators in diverse biological processes. How- ever, little is known about their cis- and trans-regulatory contributions in gene expression under salt stress. Using 27 RNA-seq data sets from Populus trichocarpa leaves, stems and roots, we identified 2988 high- confidence lncRNAs, including 1183 salt-induced differentially expressed lncRNAs. Among them, 301 lncRNAs have potential for positively affecting their neighboring genes, predominantly in a cis-regulatory manner rather than by co-transcription. Additionally, a co-expression network identified six striking salt- associated modules with a total of 5639 genes, including 426 lncRNAs, and in these lncRNA sequences, the DNA/RNA binding motifs are enriched. This suggests that lncRNAs might contribute to distant gene expres- sion of the salt-associated modules in a trans-regulatory manner. Moreover, we found 30 lncRNAs that have potential to simultaneously cis- and trans-regulate salt-responsive homologous genes, and Ptlinc-NAC72, significantly induced under long-term salt stress, was selected for validating its regulation of the expression and functional roles of the homologs PtNAC72.A and PtNAC72.B (PtNAC72.A/B). The transient transforma- tion of Ptlinc-NAC72 and a dual-luciferase assay of Ptlinc-NAC72 and PtNAC72.A/B promoters confirmed that Ptlinc-NAC72 can directly upregulate PtNAC72.A/B expression, and a presence/absence assay was fur- ther conducted to show that the regulation is probably mediated by Ptlinc-NAC72 recognizing the tandem elements (GAAAAA) in the PtNAC72.A/B 50 untranslated region (50-UTR). Finally, the overexpression of Ptlinc-NAC72 produces a hypersensitive phenotype under salt stress. Altogether, our results shed light on the cis- and trans-regulation of gene expression by lncRNAs in Populus and provides an example of long- term salt-induced Ptlinc-NAC72 that could be used to mitigate growth costs by conferring plant resilience to salt stress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-the-plant-journal-2022&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/tpj.15714&quot;&gt;the Plant Journal (2022)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;``&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/05/17/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/05/17/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>ReFeaFi: Genome-wide prediction of regulatory elements driving transcription initiation</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regulatory elements control gene expression through transcription initiation (promoters) and by enhancing transcription at distant regions (enhancers). Accurate identification of reg- ulatory elements is fundamental for annotating genomes and understanding gene expres- sion patterns. While there are many attempts to develop computational promoter and enhancer identification methods, reliable tools to analyze long genomic sequences are still lacking. Prediction methods often perform poorly on the genome-wide scale because the number of negatives is much higher than that in the training sets. To address this issue, we propose a dynamic negative set updating scheme with a two-model approach, using one model for scanning the genome and the other one for testing candidate positions. The devel- oped method achieves good genome-level performance and maintains robust performance when applied to other vertebrate species, without re-training. Moreover, the unannotated predicted regulatory regions made on the human genome are enriched for disease-associ- ated variants, suggesting them to be potentially true regulatory elements rather than false positives. We validated high scoring “false positive” predictions using reporter assay and all tested candidates were successfully validated, demonstrating the ability of our method to discover novel human regulatory regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-plos-computational-biology-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.1009376&quot;&gt;Plos Computational Biology (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/05/11/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/05/11/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Chromatin accessibility landscape and regulatory network of high-altitude hypoxia adaptation</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High-altitude adaptation of Tibetans represents a remarkable case of natural selection during recent human evolution. Previous genome-wide scans found many non-coding variants under selection, suggesting a pressing need to understand the functional role of non-coding reg- ulatory elements (REs). Here, we generate time courses of paired ATAC-seq and RNA-seq data on cultured HUVECs under hypoxic and normoxic conditions. We further develop a variant interpretation methodology (vPECA) to identify active selected REs (ASREs) and associated regulatory network. We discover three causal SNPs of EPAS1, the key adaptive gene for Tibetans. These SNPs decrease the accessibility of ASREs with weakened binding strength of relevant TFs, and cooperatively down-regulate EPAS1 expression. We further construct the downstream network of EPAS1, elucidating its roles in hypoxic response and angiogenesis. Collectively, we provide a systematic approach to interpret phenotype- associated noncoding variants in proper cell types and relevant dynamic conditions, to model their impact on gene regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-communication-2020&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-020-18638-8&quot;&gt;Nature Communication (2020)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/04/26/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/04/26/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>DNA methylation-free Arabidopsis reveals crucial roles of DNA methylation in regulating gene expression and development</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A contribution of DNA methylation to defense against invading nucleic acids and maintenance of genome integrity is uncontested; however, our understanding of the extent of involvement of this epigenetic mark in genome-wide gene regulation and plant developmental control is incomplete. Here, we knock out all five known DNA methyltransferases in Arabidopsis, generating DNA methylation-free plants. This quintuple mutant exhibits a suite of developmental defects, unequivocally demonstrating that DNA methylation is essential for multiple aspects of plant development. We show that CG methylation and non-CG methylation are required for a plethora of biological processes, including pavement cell shape, endoreduplication, cell death, flowering, trichome morphology, vasculature and meristem development, and root cell fate determination. Moreover, we find that DNA methylation has a strong dose-dependent effect on gene expression and repression of transposable elements. Taken together, our results demonstrate that DNA methylation is dispensable for Arabidopsis survival but essential for the proper regulation of multiple biological processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-communications-2022&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-022-28940-2&quot;&gt;Nature Communications (2022)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/04/19/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/04/19/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>ReFeaFi: Genome-wide prediction of regulatory elements driving transcription initiation</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regulatory elements control gene expression through transcription initiation (promoters) and by enhancing transcription at distant regions (enhancers). Accurate identification of regulatory elements is fundamental for annotating genomes and understanding gene expression patterns. While there are many attempts to develop computational promoter and enhancer identification methods, reliable tools to analyze long genomic sequences are still lacking. Prediction methods often perform poorly on the genome-wide scale because the number of negatives is much higher than that in the training sets. To address this issue, we propose a dynamic negative set updating scheme with a two-model approach, using one model for scanning the genome and the other one for testing candidate positions. The developed method achieves good genome-level performance and maintains robust performance when applied to other vertebrate species, without re-training. Moreover, the unannotated predicted regulatory regions made on the human genome are enriched for disease-associated variants, suggesting them to be potentially true regulatory elements rather than false positives. We validated high scoring “false positive” predictions using reporter assay and all tested candidates were successfully validated, demonstrating the ability of our method to discover novel human regulatory regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-plos-computational-biology-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.1009376&quot;&gt;PLOS Computational Biology (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/04/13/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/04/13/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A comprehensive catalog of predicted functional upstream open reading frames in humans</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upstream open reading frames (uORFs) latent in mRNA transcripts are thought to modify translation of coding sequences by altering ribosome activity. Not all uORFs are thought to be active in such a pro- cess. To estimate the impact of uORFs on the regula- tion of translation in humans, we first circumscribed the universe of all possible uORFs based on cod- ing gene sequence motifs and identified 1.3 million unique uORFs. To determine which of these are likely to be biologically relevant, we built a simple Bayesian classifier using 89 attributes of uORFs labeled as ac- tive in ribosome profiling experiments. This allowed us to extrapolate to a comprehensive catalog of likely functional uORFs. We validated our predictions us- ing in vivo protein levels and ribosome occupancy from 46 individuals. This is a substantially larger cat- alog of functional uORFs than has previously been reported. Our ranked list of likely active uORFs al- lows researchers to test their hypotheses regarding the role of uORFs in health and disease. We demon- strate several examples of biological interest through the application of our catalog to somatic mutations in cancer and disease-associated germline variants in humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nucleic-acids-research-2018&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/nar/article/46/7/3326/4942470&quot;&gt;Nucleic Acids Research (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/04/06/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/04/06/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>ALK, the Key Gene for Gelatinization Temperature, is a Modifier Gene for Gel Consistency in Rice</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gelatinization temperature (GT) is an important parameter in evaluating the cooking and eating quality of rice. Indeed, the phenotype, biochemistry and inheritance of GT have been widely studied in recent times. Previous map-based cloning revealed that GT was controlled by ALK gene, which encodes a putative soluble starch synthase II-3. Complementation vector and RNAi vector were constructed and transformed into Nipponbare mediated by Agrobacterium. Phenotypic and molecular analyses of transgenic lines provided direct evidence for ALK as a key gene for GT. Meanwhile, amylose content, gel consistency and pasting properties were also affected in transgenic lines. Two of four nonsynonymous single nucleotide polymorphisms in coding sequence of ALK were identified as essential for GT. Based on the single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs), two new sets of SNP markers combined with one cleaved amplified polymorphic sequence marker were developed for application in rice quality breeding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-journal-of-integrative-plant-biology-2011&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1744-7909.2011.01065.x&quot;&gt;Journal of Integrative Plant Biology (2011)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/03/30/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/03/30/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Linker histones are fine-scale chromatin architects modulating developmental decisions in Arabidopsis</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chromatin provides a tunable platform for gene expression control. Besides the well-studied core nucleosome, H1 linker histones are abundant chromatin components with intrinsic potential to influence chromatin function. Well studied in animals, little is known about the evolution of H1 function in other eukaryotic lineages for instance plants. Notably, in the model plant Arabidopsis, while H1 is known to influence heterochromatin and DNA methylation, its contribution to transcription, molecular, and cytological chromatin organization remains elusive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We provide a multi-scale functional study of Arabidopsis linker histones. We show that H1-deficient plants are viable yet show phenotypes in seed dormancy, flowering time, lateral root, and stomata formation— complemented by either or both of the major variants. H1 depletion also impairs pluripotent callus formation. Fine- scale chromatin analyses combined with transcriptome and nucleosome profiling reveal distinct roles of H1 on hetero- and euchromatin: H1 is necessary to form heterochromatic domains yet dispensable for silencing of most transposable elements; H1 depletion affects nucleosome density distribution and mobility in euchromatin, spatial arrangement of nanodomains, histone acetylation, and methylation. These drastic changes affect moderately the transcription but reveal a subset of H1-sensitive genes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;H1 variants have a profound impact on the molecular and spatial (nuclear) chromatin organization in Arabidopsis with distinct roles in euchromatin and heterochromatin and a dual causality on gene expression. Phenotypical analyses further suggest the novel possibility that H1-mediated chromatin organization may contribute to the epigenetic control of developmental and cellular transitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-genome-biology-2019&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1186/s13059-019-1767-3&quot;&gt;Genome Biology (2019)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/03/23/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/03/23/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The two clock proteins CCA1 and LHY activate VIN3 transcription during vernalization through the vernalization-responsive cis-element</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vernalization, a long-term cold-mediated acquisition of flowering competence, is critically regulated by VERNALIZATION INSENSITIVE 3 (VIN3), a gene induced by vernalization in Arabidopsis. Although the function of VIN3 has been extensively studied, how VIN3 expression itself is upregulated by long-term cold is not well understood. In this study, we identified a vernalization-responsive cis-element in the VIN3 promoter, VREVIN3, composed of a G-box and an evening element (EE). Mutations in either the G-box or the EE prevented VIN3 expression from being fully induced upon vernalization, leading to defects in the vernalization response. We determined that the core clock proteins CIRCADIAN CLOCK-ASSOCIATED 1 (CCA1) and LATE-ELONGATED HYPOCOTYL (LHY) associate with the EE of VREVIN3, both in vitro and in vivo. In a cca1 lhy double mutant background harboring a functional FRIGIDA allele, long-term cold-mediated VIN3 induction and acceler- ation of flowering were impaired, especially under mild cold conditions such as at 12􏰂C. During prolonged cold exposure, oscillations of CCA1/LHY transcripts were altered, while CCA1 abundance increased at dusk, coinciding with the diurnal peak of VIN3 transcripts. We propose that modulation of the clock proteins CCA1 and LHY participates in the systems in- volved in sensing long-term cold for the activation of VIN3 transcription.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-plant-cell-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/plcell/article-abstract/34/3/1020/6472367&quot;&gt;Plant Cell (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/03/14/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/03/14/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
