<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Zhang Tao lab</title>
    <description>Bioinformatics, Epigenetics and Genomics.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jun 2021 21:06:06 +0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Jun 2021 21:06:06 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Natural variations of SLG1 confer high-temperature tolerance in indica rice</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With global warming and climate change, breeding crop plants tolerant to high-temperature stress is of immense significance. tRNA 2-thiolation is a highly conserved form of tRNA modification among living organisms. Here, we report the identification of SLG1 (Slender Guy 1), which encodes the cytosolic tRNA 2-thiolation protein 2 (RCTU2) in rice. SLG1 plays a key role in the response of rice plants to high-temperature stress at both seedling and reproductive stages. Dysfunction of SLG1 results in plants with thermosensitive phenotype, while overexpression of SLG1 enhances the tolerance of plants to high temperature. SLG1 is differentiated between the two Asian cultivated rice subspecies, indica and japonica, and the variations at both promoter and coding regions lead to an increased level of thiolated tRNA and enhanced thermotolerance of indica rice varieties. Our results demonstrate that the allelic differentiation of SLG1 confers indica rice to high-temperature tolerance, and tRNA thiolation pathway might be a potential target in the next generation rice breeding for the warming globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-communication-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-020-19320-9&quot;&gt;Nature Communication (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/06/13/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/06/13/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Single-nucleotide-level mapping of DNA regulatory elements that control fetal hemoglobin expression</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pinpointing functional noncoding DNA sequences and defining their contributions to health-related traits is a major challenge for modern genetics. We developed a high-throughput framework to map noncoding DNA functions with single-nucleotide resolution in four loci that control erythroid fetal hemoglobin (HbF) expression, a genetically determined trait that modifies sickle cell disease (SCD) phenotypes. Specifically, we used the adenine base editor ABEmax to introduce 10,156 separate A•T to G•C conversions in 307 predicted regulatory elements and quantified the effects on erythroid HbF expression. We identified numerous regulatory elements, defined their epigenomic structures and linked them to low-frequency variants associated with HbF expression in an SCD cohort. Targeting a newly discovered γ-globin gene repressor element in SCD donor CD34+ hematopoietic progenitors raised HbF levels in the erythroid progeny, inhibiting hypoxia-induced sickling. Our findings reveal previously unappreciated genetic complexities of HbF regulation and provide potentially therapeutic insights into SCD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-genetics-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41588-021-00861-8&quot;&gt;Nature Genetics (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/05/30/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/05/30/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Chromothripsis as an on-target consequence of CRISPR–Cas9 genome editing</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genome editing has therapeutic potential for treating genetic diseases and cancer. However, the currently most practicable approaches rely on the generation of DNA double-strand breaks (DSBs), which can give rise to a poorly characterized spectrum of chromosome structural abnormalities. Here, using model cells and single-cell whole-genome sequencing, as well as by editing at a clinically relevant locus in clinically relevant cells, we show that CRISPR–Cas9 editing generates structural defects of the nucleus, micronuclei and chromosome bridges, which initiate a mutational process called chromothripsis. Chromothripsis is extensive chromosome rearrangement restricted to one or a few chromosomes that can cause human congenital disease and cancer. These results demonstrate that chromothripsis is a previously unappreciated on-target consequence of CRISPR–Cas9-generated DSBs. As genome editing is implemented in the clinic, the potential for extensive chromosomal rearrangements should be considered and monitored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-genetics-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41588-021-00838-7&quot;&gt;Nature Genetics (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 23 May 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/05/23/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/05/23/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Integrative inference of transcriptional networks in Arabidopsis yields novel ROS signalling regulators</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gene regulation is a dynamic process in which transcription factors (TFs) play an important role in controlling spatiotemporal gene expression. To enhance our global understanding of regulatory interactions in Arabidopsis thaliana, different regulatory input networks capturing complementary information about DNA motifs, open chromatin, TF-binding and expression-based regulatory interactions were combined using a supervised learning approach, resulting in an integrated gene regulatory net- work (iGRN) covering 1,491 TFs and 31,393 target genes (1.7 million interactions). This iGRN outperforms the different input networks to predict known regulatory interactions and has a similar performance to recover functional interactions compared to state-of-the-art experimental methods. The iGRN correctly inferred known functions for 681 TFs and predicted new gene functions for hundreds of unknown TFs. For regulators predicted to be involved in reactive oxygen species (ROS) stress regu- lation, we confirmed in total 75% of TFs with a function in ROS and/or physiological stress responses. This includes 13 ROS regulators, previously not connected to any ROS or stress function, that were experimentally validated in our ROS-specific phenotypic assays of loss- or gain-of-function lines. In conclusion, the presented iGRN offers a high-quality starting point to enhance our understanding of gene regulation in plants by integrating different experimental data types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-plants-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41477-021-00894-1&quot;&gt;Nature Plants (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 May 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/05/17/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/05/17/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: A high-quality genome assembly highlights rye genomic characteristics and agronomically important genes</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rye is a valuable food and forage crop, an important genetic resource for wheat and triticale improvement and an indispensable material for efficient comparative genomic studies in grasses. Here, we sequenced the genome of Weining rye, an elite Chinese rye variety. The assembled contigs (7.74 Gb) accounted for 98.47% of the estimated genome size (7.86 Gb), with 93.67% of the contigs (7.25 Gb) assigned to seven chromosomes. Repetitive elements constituted 90.31% of the assembled genome. Compared to previously sequenced Triticeae genomes, Daniela, Sumaya and Sumana retrotransposons showed strong expansion in rye. Further analyses of the Weining assembly shed new light on genome-wide gene duplications and their impact on starch biosynthesis genes, physical organization of complex prolamin loci, gene expression features underlying early heading trait and putative domestication-associated chromosomal regions and loci in rye. This genome sequence promises to accelerate genomic and breeding studies in rye and related cereal crops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-genetics-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41588-021-00808-z&quot;&gt;Nature Genetics (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/05/10/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/05/10/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Unidirectional movement of small RNAs from shoots to roots in interspecific heterograf</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long-distance RNA movement is important for plant growth and environmental responses; however, the extent to which RNAs move between distant tissues, their relative magnitude and functional importance remain to be elucidated on a genomic scale. Using a soybean (Glycine max)–common bean (Phaseolus vulgaris) grafting system, we identified 100 shoot–root mobile microRNAs and 32 shoot–root mobile phased secondary small interfering RNAs (phasiRNAs), which were predominantly pro- duced in shoots and transported to roots, and, in most cases, accumulated to a level similar to that observed in shoots. Many of these microRNAs or phasiRNAs enabled cleavage of their messenger RNA targets or phasiRNA precursors in roots. In contrast, most mobile-capable mRNAs were transcribed in both shoots and roots, with only small proportions transported to recipient tissues. These findings suggest that the regulatory mechanisms for small RNA movement are different from those for mRNA movement, and that the former is more strictly regulated and, probably, more functionally important than the latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-plants-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41477-020-00829-2&quot;&gt;Nature Plants (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/04/25/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/04/25/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: G-protein βγ subunits determine grain size through interaction with MADS-domain transcription factors in rice</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simultaneous improvement of grain quality and yield of cereal crops is a major challenge for modern agriculture. Here we show that a rice grain yield quantitative trait locus qLGY3 encodes a MADS-domain transcription factor OsMADS1, which acts as a key downstream effector of G-protein βγ dimers. The presence of an alternatively spliced protein OsMADS1&lt;sup&gt;lgy3&lt;/sup&gt; is shown to be associated with formation of long and slender grains, resulting in increases in both grain quality and yield potential of rice. The Gγ subunits GS3 and DEP1 interact directly with the conserved keratin-like domain of MADS transcription factors, function as cofactors to enhance OsMADS1 transcriptional activity and promote the co-operative transactivation of common target genes, thereby regulating grain size and shape. We also demonstrate that combining OsMADS1&lt;sup&gt;lgy3&lt;/sup&gt; allele with high-yield-associated dep1-1 and gs3 alleles represents an effective strategy for simultaneously improving both the productivity and end-use quality of rice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-communications-2018&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-018-03047-9&quot;&gt;Nature Communications (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/04/16/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/04/16/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Molecular Networks of Seed Size Control in Plants</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The size of seeds affects not only evolutionary fitness but also grain yield of crops. Understanding the mechanisms controlling seed size has become an important research field in plant science. Seed size is determined by the integrated signals of maternal and zygotic tissues, which control the coordinated growth of the embryo, endosperm, and seed coat. Recent advances have identified several signaling pathways that control seed size through maternal tissues, including or involving the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway, G-protein signaling, mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) signaling, phytohormone perception and homeostasis, and some transcriptional regulators. Meanwhile, growth of the zygotic tissues is regulated in part by the HAIKU (IKU) pathway and phytohormones. This review provides a general overview of current findings in seed size control and discusses the emerging molecular mechanisms and regulatory networks found to be involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-annual-review-of-plant-biology-2019&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.annualreviews.org/doi/10.1146/annurev-arplant-050718-095851&quot;&gt;Annual Review of Plant Biology (2019)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/04/11/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/04/11/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Identification of Plant Enhancers and Their Constituent Elements by STARR-seq in Tobacco Leaves</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genetic engineering of cis-regulatory elements in crop plants is a promising strategy to ensure food security. However, such engineering is currently hindered by our limited knowledge of plant cis-regulatory elements. Here, we adapted self-transcribing active regulatory region sequencing (STARR-seq)—a technology for the high-throughput identification of enhancers—for its use in transiently transformed tobacco (Nicotiana benthamiana) leaves. We demonstrate that the optimal placement in the reporter construct of enhancer sequences from a plant virus, pea (Pisum sativum) and wheat (Triticum aestivum), was just upstream of a minimal promoter and that none of these four known enhancers was active in the 39 untranslated region of the reporter gene. The optimized assay sensitively identified small DNA regions containing each of the four enhancers, including two whose activity was stimulated by light. Furthermore, we coupled the assay to saturation mutagenesis to pinpoint functional regions within an enhancer, which we recombined to create synthetic enhancers. Our results describe an approach to define enhancer properties that can be performed in potentially any plant species or tissue transformable by Agrobacterium and that can use regulatory DNA derived from any plant genome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-the-plant-cell-2020&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/plcell/article/32/7/2120/6115620&quot;&gt;The Plant Cell (2020)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 04 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/04/04/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/04/04/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Epigenetic reprogramming rewires transcription during the alternation of generations in Arabidopsis</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternation between morphologically distinct haploid and diploid life forms is a defining feature of most plant and algal life cycles, yet the underlying molecular mechanisms that govern these transitions remain unclear. Here, we explore the dynamic relationship between chromatin accessibility and epigenetic modifications during life form transitions in Arabidopsis. The diploid-to-haploid life form transition is governed by the loss of H3K9me2 and DNA demethylation of transposon-associated cis-regulatory elements. This event is associated with dramatic changes in chromatin accessibility and transcriptional reprogramming. In contrast, the global loss of H3K27me3 in the haploid form shapes a chromatin accessibility landscape that is poised to re-initiate the transition back to diploid life after fertilisation. Hence, distinct epigenetic reprogramming events rewire transcription through major reorganisation of the regulatory epigenome to guide the alternation of generations in flowering plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-elife-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://elifesciences.org/articles/61894&quot;&gt;eLife (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/03/20/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/03/20/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
