<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Zhang Tao lab</title>
    <description>Bioinformatics, Epigenetics and Genomics.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 18:55:59 +0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 18:55:59 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>ALK, the Key Gene for Gelatinization Temperature, is a Modifier Gene for Gel Consistency in Rice</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gelatinization temperature (GT) is an important parameter in evaluating the cooking and eating quality of rice. Indeed, the phenotype, biochemistry and inheritance of GT have been widely studied in recent times. Previous map-based cloning revealed that GT was controlled by ALK gene, which encodes a putative soluble starch synthase II-3. Complementation vector and RNAi vector were constructed and transformed into Nipponbare mediated by Agrobacterium. Phenotypic and molecular analyses of transgenic lines provided direct evidence for ALK as a key gene for GT. Meanwhile, amylose content, gel consistency and pasting properties were also affected in transgenic lines. Two of four nonsynonymous single nucleotide polymorphisms in coding sequence of ALK were identified as essential for GT. Based on the single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs), two new sets of SNP markers combined with one cleaved amplified polymorphic sequence marker were developed for application in rice quality breeding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-journal-of-integrative-plant-biology-2011&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1744-7909.2011.01065.x&quot;&gt;Journal of Integrative Plant Biology (2011)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/03/30/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/03/30/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Linker histones are fine-scale chromatin architects modulating developmental decisions in Arabidopsis</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chromatin provides a tunable platform for gene expression control. Besides the well-studied core nucleosome, H1 linker histones are abundant chromatin components with intrinsic potential to influence chromatin function. Well studied in animals, little is known about the evolution of H1 function in other eukaryotic lineages for instance plants. Notably, in the model plant Arabidopsis, while H1 is known to influence heterochromatin and DNA methylation, its contribution to transcription, molecular, and cytological chromatin organization remains elusive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We provide a multi-scale functional study of Arabidopsis linker histones. We show that H1-deficient plants are viable yet show phenotypes in seed dormancy, flowering time, lateral root, and stomata formation— complemented by either or both of the major variants. H1 depletion also impairs pluripotent callus formation. Fine- scale chromatin analyses combined with transcriptome and nucleosome profiling reveal distinct roles of H1 on hetero- and euchromatin: H1 is necessary to form heterochromatic domains yet dispensable for silencing of most transposable elements; H1 depletion affects nucleosome density distribution and mobility in euchromatin, spatial arrangement of nanodomains, histone acetylation, and methylation. These drastic changes affect moderately the transcription but reveal a subset of H1-sensitive genes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;H1 variants have a profound impact on the molecular and spatial (nuclear) chromatin organization in Arabidopsis with distinct roles in euchromatin and heterochromatin and a dual causality on gene expression. Phenotypical analyses further suggest the novel possibility that H1-mediated chromatin organization may contribute to the epigenetic control of developmental and cellular transitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-genome-biology-2019&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1186/s13059-019-1767-3&quot;&gt;Genome Biology (2019)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/03/23/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/03/23/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The two clock proteins CCA1 and LHY activate VIN3 transcription during vernalization through the vernalization-responsive cis-element</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vernalization, a long-term cold-mediated acquisition of flowering competence, is critically regulated by VERNALIZATION INSENSITIVE 3 (VIN3), a gene induced by vernalization in Arabidopsis. Although the function of VIN3 has been extensively studied, how VIN3 expression itself is upregulated by long-term cold is not well understood. In this study, we identified a vernalization-responsive cis-element in the VIN3 promoter, VREVIN3, composed of a G-box and an evening element (EE). Mutations in either the G-box or the EE prevented VIN3 expression from being fully induced upon vernalization, leading to defects in the vernalization response. We determined that the core clock proteins CIRCADIAN CLOCK-ASSOCIATED 1 (CCA1) and LATE-ELONGATED HYPOCOTYL (LHY) associate with the EE of VREVIN3, both in vitro and in vivo. In a cca1 lhy double mutant background harboring a functional FRIGIDA allele, long-term cold-mediated VIN3 induction and acceler- ation of flowering were impaired, especially under mild cold conditions such as at 12􏰂C. During prolonged cold exposure, oscillations of CCA1/LHY transcripts were altered, while CCA1 abundance increased at dusk, coinciding with the diurnal peak of VIN3 transcripts. We propose that modulation of the clock proteins CCA1 and LHY participates in the systems in- volved in sensing long-term cold for the activation of VIN3 transcription.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-plant-cell-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/plcell/article-abstract/34/3/1020/6472367&quot;&gt;Plant Cell (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/03/14/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/03/14/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A quantitative genomics map of rice provides genetic insights and guides breeding</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extensive allelic variation in agronomically important genes serves as the basis of rice breeding. Here, we present a comprehen- sive map of rice quantitative trait nucleotides (QTNs) and inferred QTN effects based on eight genome-wide association study cohorts. Population genetic analyses revealed that domestication, local adaptation and heterosis are all associated with QTN allele frequency changes. A genome navigation system, RiceNavi, was developed for QTN pyramiding and breeding route opti- mization, and implemented in the improvement of a widely cultivated indica variety. This work presents an efficient platform that bridges ever-increasing genomic knowledge and diverse improvement needs in rice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-genetics-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41588-020-00769-9&quot;&gt;Nature Genetics (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/03/07/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/03/07/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A uORF Represses the Transcription Factor AtHB1 in Aerial Tissues to Avoid a Deleterious Phenotype</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AtHB1 is an Arabidopsis (Arabidopsis thaliana) homeodomain-leucine zipper transcription factor that participates in hypocotyl elongation under short-day conditions. Here, we show that its expression is posttranscriptionally regulated by an upstream open reading frame (uORF) located in its 5′ untranslated region. This uORF encodes a highly conserved peptide (CPuORF) that is present in varied monocot and dicot species. The Arabidopsis uORF and its maize (Zea mays) homolog repressed the translation of the main open reading frame in cis, independent of the sequence of the latter. Published ribosome footprinting results and the analysis of a frame-shifted uORF, in which the repression capability was lost, indicated that the uORF causes ribosome stalling. The regulation exerted by the CPuORF was tissue specific and did not act in the absence of light. Moreover, a photosynthetic signal is needed for the CPuORF action, since plants with uncoupled chloroplasts did not show uORF-dependent repression. Plants transformed with the native AtHB1 promoter driving AtHB1 expression did not show differential phenotypes, whereas those transformed with a construct in which the uORF was mutated exhibited serrated leaves, compact rosettes, and, most significantly, short nondehiscent anthers and siliques containing fewer or no seeds. Thus, we propose that the uncontrolled expression of AtHB1 is deleterious for the plant and, hence, finely repressed by a translational mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-plant-physiology-2017&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/plphys/article/175/3/1238/6116883&quot;&gt;Plant Physiology (2017)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/01/09/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/01/09/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Enhancing rice grain production by manipulating the naturally evolved cis-regulatory element-containing inverted repeat sequence of OsREM20</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grain number per panicle (GNP) is an important agronomic trait that contributes to rice grain yield. Despite its importance in rice breeding, the molecular mechanism underlying GNP regulation remains largely unknown. In this study, we identified a previously unrecognized regulatory gene that controls GNP in rice, Oryza sativa REPRODUCTIVE MERISTEM 20 (OsREM20), which encodes a B3 domain transcription factor. Through genetic analysis and transgenic validation we found that genetic variation in the CArG box-containing inverted repeat (IR) sequence of the OsREM20 promoter alters its expression level and contributes to GNP variation among rice varieties. Furthermore, we revealed that the IR sequence regulates OsREM20 expression by affecting the direct binding of OsMADS34 to the CArG box within the IR sequence. Interestingly, the divergent pOsREM20IR and pOsREM20ΔIR alleles were found to originate from different Oryza rufipogon accessions, and were independently inherited into the japonica and indica subspecies, respectively, during domestication. Importantly, we demonstrated that IR sequence variations in the OsREM20 promoter can be utilized for germplasm improvement through either genome editing or traditional breeding. Taken together, our study characterizes novel genetic variations responsible for GNP diversity in rice, reveals the underlying molecular mechanism in the regulation of agronomically important gene expression, and provides a promising strategy for improving rice production by manipulating the cis-regulatory element-containing IR sequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-molecular-plant-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S1674205221000915&quot;&gt;Molecular Plant (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/12/12/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/12/12/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Assessing genome-wide dynamic changes in enhancer activity during early mESC differentiation by FAIRE-STARR-seq</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Embryonic stem cells (ESCs) can differentiate into any given cell type and therefore represent a versatile model to study the link between gene regulation and differentiation. To quantitatively assess the dynamics of enhancer activity during the early stages of murine ESC differentiation, we analyzed accessible genomic regions using STARR-seq, a massively parallel reporter assay. This resulted in a genome-wide quantitative map of active mESC enhancers, in pluripotency and during the early stages of differentiation. We find that only a minority of accessible regions is active and that such regions are enriched near promoters, characterized by specific chromatin marks, enriched for distinct sequence motifs, and modeling shows that active regions can be predicted from sequence alone. Regions that change their activity upon retinoic acid-induced differentiation are more prevalent at distal intergenic regions when compared to constitutively active enhancers. Further, analysis of differentially active enhancers verified the contribution of individual TF motifs toward activity and inducibility as well as their role in regulating endogenous genes. Notably, the activity of retinoic acid receptor alpha (RARα) occupied regions can either increase or decrease upon the addition of its ligand, retinoic acid, with the direction of the change correlating with spacing and orientation of the RARα consensus motif and the co-occurrence of additional sequence motifs. Together, our genome-wide enhancer activity map elucidates features associated with enhancer activity levels, identifies regulatory regions disregarded by computational prediction tools, and provides a resource for future studies into regulatory elements in mESCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nucleic-acids-research-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/nar/article/49/21/12178/6438040&quot;&gt;Nucleic Acids Research (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/12/05/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/12/05/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Quantitative regulation of Waxy expression by CRISPR/Cas9-based promoter and 5’UTR-intron editing improves grain quality in rice</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In cereal crops, grain starches are composed of different proportions of amylose and amylopectin, which determine the cooking and eating qualities. The amylose synthesis is controlled by the Waxy (Wx) gene encoding a granule bound NDP-glucose- starch glucosyltransferase (Shure et al., 1983). In rice (Oryza sativa L.), the varied activities of natural Wx alleles regulate different amylose contents (AC), gel consistency (GC) and pasting viscosity of grain starches; these factors together influence the grain appearance, cooking/eating quality and starch physical characters (Zhang et al., 2019). Wxa is a strong allele mainly distributing in indica (an O. sativa subspecies) cultivars producing high ACs (25%–30%) (Wang et al., 1995). While Wxb, presenting mainly in japonica (another subspecies) cultivars, is a weak allele producing moderate ACs (15–18%) (Isshiki et al., 1998). Generally, rice grains with higher ACs and lower GC values have poor eating quality, while those with moderate ACs (15–20%) and higher GC values (60–80 mm) give better taste for most consumers. Using the successive backcrossing methods, Wxb can be introgressed into indica varieties to improve the grain quality. However, the traditional breeding methods are time consuming and difficult to break close linkage drags with undesirable traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-plant-biotechnology-journal-2020&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/pbi.13427&quot;&gt;Plant Biotechnology Journal (2020)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/11/21/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/11/21/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nucleolar histone deacetylases HDT1, HDT2 and HDT3 regulate plant reproductive development</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nucleolus is a membrane-less organelle where ribosomes are assembled and rRNAs transcribed and processed. The assembled ribosomes composed of ribosomal proteins and rRNAs synthesize proteins for cell survival. In plants, the loss of nucleolar ribosomal proteins often causes gametophytically or embryonically lethality. The amount of rRNAs are under stringent regulation according to demand and partially switched off by epigenetic modifications. However, the molecular mechanism for the selective activation or silencing is still unclear, and the transcriptional coordination of rRNAs and ribosomal proteins is also unknown. Here we report the critical role of three Arabidopsis nucleolar protein HDT1, HDT2 and HDT3 in fertility and transcription of rDNAs and rRNA processing-related genes through histone acetylation. This study highlights the important roles of transcriptional repression of ribosome biogenesis-related genes for plant reproductive development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-journal-of-genetics-and-genomics-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S1673852721003246?via%3Dihub&quot;&gt;Journal of Genetics and Genomics (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/11/15/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/11/15/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Plastidic Pyruvate Dehydrogenase Complex E1 Component Subunit Alpha1 Is Involved in Galactolipid Biosynthesis Required for Amyloplast Development in Rice</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starch accounts for over 80% of the total dry weight in cereal endosperm and determines the kernel texture and nutritional quality. Amyloplasts, terminally differentiated plastids, are responsible for starch biosynthesis and storage. We screened a series of rice mutants with floury endosperm to clarify the mechanism underlying amyloplast development and starch synthesis. We identified the floury endosperm19 (flo19) mutant which shows opaque of the interior endosperm. Abnormal compound starch grains (SGs) were present in the endosperm cells of the mutant. Molecular cloning revealed that the FLO19 allele encodes a plastid-localized pyruvate dehydrogenase complex E1 component subunit α1 (ptPDC-E1-α1) that is expressed in all rice tissues. In vivo enzyme assays demonstrated that the flo19 mutant showed decreased activity of the plastidic pyruvate dehydrogenase complex. In addition, the amounts of monogalactosyldiacylglycerol (MGDG) and digalactosyldiacylglycerol (DGDG) were much lower in the developing flo19 mutant endosperm, suggesting that FLO19 participates in fatty acid supply for galactolipid biosynthesis in amyloplasts. FLO19 overexpression significantly increased seed size and weight, but did not affect other important agronomic traits, such as panicle length, tiller number and seed setting rate. An analysis of single-nucleotide polymorphism data from a panel of rice accessions identified that the pFLO19L haplotype was positively associated with grain length, implying a potential application in rice breeding. In summary, our study demonstrates that FLO19 is involved in galactolipid biosynthesis which is essential for amyloplast development and starch biosynthesis in rice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-plant-biotechnology-journal-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/pbi.13727&quot;&gt;Plant Biotechnology Journal (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/11/08/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/11/08/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
