<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Zhang Tao lab</title>
    <description>Bioinformatics, Epigenetics and Genomics.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2021 10:12:33 +0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2021 10:12:33 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nucleolar histone deacetylases HDT1, HDT2 and HDT3 regulate plant reproductive development</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nucleolus is a membrane-less organelle where ribosomes are assembled and rRNAs transcribed and processed. The assembled ribosomes composed of ribosomal proteins and rRNAs synthesize proteins for cell survival. In plants, the loss of nucleolar ribosomal proteins often causes gametophytically or embryonically lethality. The amount of rRNAs are under stringent regulation according to demand and partially switched off by epigenetic modifications. However, the molecular mechanism for the selective activation or silencing is still unclear, and the transcriptional coordination of rRNAs and ribosomal proteins is also unknown. Here we report the critical role of three Arabidopsis nucleolar protein HDT1, HDT2 and HDT3 in fertility and transcription of rDNAs and rRNA processing-related genes through histone acetylation. This study highlights the important roles of transcriptional repression of ribosome biogenesis-related genes for plant reproductive development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-journal-of-genetics-and-genomics-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S1673852721003246?via%3Dihub&quot;&gt;Journal of Genetics and Genomics (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/11/15/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/11/15/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Plastidic Pyruvate Dehydrogenase Complex E1 Component Subunit Alpha1 Is Involved in Galactolipid Biosynthesis Required for Amyloplast Development in Rice</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starch accounts for over 80% of the total dry weight in cereal endosperm and determines the kernel texture and nutritional quality. Amyloplasts, terminally differentiated plastids, are responsible for starch biosynthesis and storage. We screened a series of rice mutants with floury endosperm to clarify the mechanism underlying amyloplast development and starch synthesis. We identified the floury endosperm19 (flo19) mutant which shows opaque of the interior endosperm. Abnormal compound starch grains (SGs) were present in the endosperm cells of the mutant. Molecular cloning revealed that the FLO19 allele encodes a plastid-localized pyruvate dehydrogenase complex E1 component subunit α1 (ptPDC-E1-α1) that is expressed in all rice tissues. In vivo enzyme assays demonstrated that the flo19 mutant showed decreased activity of the plastidic pyruvate dehydrogenase complex. In addition, the amounts of monogalactosyldiacylglycerol (MGDG) and digalactosyldiacylglycerol (DGDG) were much lower in the developing flo19 mutant endosperm, suggesting that FLO19 participates in fatty acid supply for galactolipid biosynthesis in amyloplasts. FLO19 overexpression significantly increased seed size and weight, but did not affect other important agronomic traits, such as panicle length, tiller number and seed setting rate. An analysis of single-nucleotide polymorphism data from a panel of rice accessions identified that the pFLO19L haplotype was positively associated with grain length, implying a potential application in rice breeding. In summary, our study demonstrates that FLO19 is involved in galactolipid biosynthesis which is essential for amyloplast development and starch biosynthesis in rice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-plant-biotechnology-journal-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/pbi.13727&quot;&gt;Plant Biotechnology Journal (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/11/08/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/11/08/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Organization and regulation of gene transcription</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The regulated transcription of genes determines cell identity and function. Recent structural studies have elucidated mechanisms that govern the regulation of transcription by RNA polymerases during the initiation and elongation phases. Microscopy studies have revealed that transcription involves the condensation of factors in the cell nucleus. A model is emerging for the transcription of protein-coding genes in which distinct transient condensates form at gene promoters and in gene bodies to concentrate the factors required for transcription initiation and elongation, respectively. The transcribing enzyme RNA polymerase II may shuttle between these condensates in a phosphorylation-dependent manner. Molecular principles are being defined that rationalize transcriptional organization and regulation, and that will guide future investigations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-2019&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-019-1517-4&quot;&gt;Nature (2019)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 31 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/10/31/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/10/31/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A photoregulatory mechanism of the circadian clock in Arabidopsis</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cryptochromes (CRYs) are photoreceptors that mediate light regulation of the circadian clock in plants and animals. Here we show that CRYs mediate blue-light regulation of N&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;-methyladenosine (m&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;A) modification of more than 10% of messenger RNAs in the Arabidopsis transcriptome, especially those regulated by the circadian clock. CRY2 interacts with three subunits of the METTL3/14-type N&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;-methyladenosine RNA methyltransferase (m&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;A writer): MTA, MTB and FIP37. Photo-excited CRY2 undergoes liquid–liquid phase separation (LLPS) to co-condense m&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;A writer proteins in vivo, without obviously altering the affinity between CRY2 and the writer proteins. mta and cry1cry2 mutants share common defects of a lengthened circadian period, reduced m&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;A RNA methylation and accelerated degradation of mRNA encoding the core component of the molecular oscillator circadian clock associated 1 (CCA1). These results argue for a photoregulatory mechanism by which light-induced phase separation of CRYs modulates m&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;A writer activity, mRNA methylation and abundance, and the circadian rhythms in plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-plants-2020&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41477-021-01002-z&quot;&gt;Nature Plants (2020)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/10/25/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/10/25/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: MAC5, an RNA-binding protein, protects pri-miRNAs from SERRATE-dependent exoribonuclease activities</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MAC5 is a component of the conserved MOS4-associated complex. It plays critical roles in development and immunity. Here we report that MAC5 is required for microRNA (miRNA) biogenesis. MAC5 interacts with Serrate (SE), which is a core component of the microprocessor that processes primary miRNA transcripts (pri-miRNAs) into miRNAs and binds the stem-loop region of pri-miRNAs. MAC5 is essential for both the efficient processing and the stability of pri-miRNAs. Interestingly, the reduction of pri-miRNA levels in &lt;em&gt;mac5&lt;/em&gt; is partially caused by XRN2/XRN3, the nuclear-localized 5′-to-3′ exoribonucleases, and depends on SE. These results reveal that MAC5 plays a dual role in promoting pri-miRNA processing and stability through its interaction with SE and/or pri-miRNAs. This study also uncovers that pri-miRNAs need to be protected from nuclear RNA decay machinery, which is connected to the microprocessor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-pnas-2020&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/117/38/23982&quot;&gt;PNAS (2020)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/10/18/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/10/18/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Determinants of genome-wide distribution and evolution of uORFs in eukaryotes</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upstream open reading frames (uORFs) play widespread regulatory functions in modulating mRNA translation in eukaryotes, but the principles underlying the genomic distribution and evolution of uORFs remain poorly understood. Here, we analyze ~17 million putative canonical uORFs in 478 eukaryotic species that span most of the extant taxa of eukaryotes. We demonstrate how positive and purifying selection, coupled with differences in effective population size (Ne), has shaped the contents of uORFs in eukaryotes. Besides, gene expression level is important in influencing uORF occurrences across genes in a species. Our analyses suggest that most uORFs might play regulatory roles rather than encode functional peptides. We also show that the Kozak sequence context of uORFs has evolved across eukaryotic clades, and that noncanonical uORFs tend to have weaker suppressive effects than canonical uORFs in translation regulation. This study provides insights into the driving forces underlying uORF evolution in eukaryotes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-communications-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-021-21394-y&quot;&gt;Nature Communications (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/10/10/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/10/10/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Analysis of gene network bifurcation during optic cup morphogenesis in zebrafish</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sight depends on the tight cooperation between photoreceptors and pigmented cells, which derive from common progenitors through the bifurcation of a single gene regulatory network into the neural retina (NR) and retinal-pigmented epithelium (RPE) programs. Although genetic studies have identified upstream nodes controlling these networks, their regulatory logic remains poorly investigated. Here, we characterize transcriptome dynamics and chromatin accessibility in segregating NR/RPE populations in zebrafish. We analyze cis-regulatory modules and enriched transcription factor motives to show extensive network redundancy and context-dependent activity. We identify downstream targets, highlighting an early recruitment of desmosomal genes in the flattening RPE and revealing Tead factors as upstream regulators. We investigate the RPE specification network dynamics to uncover an unexpected sequence of transcription factors recruitment, which is conserved in humans. This systematic interrogation of the NR/RPE bifurcation should improve both genetic counseling for eye disorders and hiPSCs-to-RPE differentiation protocols for cell-replacement therapies in degenerative diseases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-communications-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-021-24169-7&quot;&gt;Nature Communications (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/09/27/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/09/27/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: RGN1 controls grain number and shapes panicle architecture in rice</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yield in rice is determined mainly by panicle architecture. Using map-based cloning we identified an R2R3 MYB transcription factor REGULATOR OF GRAIN NUMBER1 (RGN1) affecting grain number and panicle architecture. Mutation of RGN1 caused an absence of lateral grains on secondary branches. We demonstrated that RGN1 controls lateral grain formation by regulation of LONELY GUY (LOG) expression, thus controlling grain number and shaping panicle architecture. A novel favorable allele, RGN1C, derived from the Or-I group in wild rice affected panicle architecture by means longer panicles. Identification of RGN1 provides a theoretical basis for understanding the molecular mechanism of lateral grain formation in rice, RGN1 will be an important gene resource for molecular breeding for higher yield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-plant-biotechnology-journal-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://genome.cshlp.org/content/31/7/1245&quot;&gt;Plant Biotechnology Journal (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/09/19/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/09/19/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Conserved noncoding sequences provide insights into regulatory sequence and loss of gene expression in maize</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thousands of species will be sequenced in the next few years; however, understanding how their genomes work, without an unlimited budget, requires both molecular and novel evolutionary approaches. We developed a sensitive sequence alignment pipeline to identify conserved noncoding sequences (CNSs) in the Andropogoneae tribe (multiple crop species descended from a common ancestor ∼18 million years ago). The Andropogoneae share similar physiology while being tremendously genomically diverse, harboring a broad range of ploidy levels, structural variation, and transposons. These contribute to the potential of Andropogoneae as a powerful system for studying CNSs and are factors we leverage to understand the function of maize CNSs. We found that 86% of CNSs were comprised of annotated features, including introns, UTRs, putative cis-regulatory elements, chromatin loop anchors, noncoding RNA (ncRNA) genes, and several transposable element superfamilies. CNSs were enriched in active regions of DNA replication in the early S phase of the mitotic cell cycle and showed different DNA methylation ratios compared to the genome-wide background. More than half of putative cis-regulatory sequences (identified via other methods) overlapped with CNSs detected in this study. Variants in CNSs were associated with gene expression levels, and CNS absence contributed to loss of gene expression. Furthermore, the evolution of CNSs was associated with the functional diversification of duplicated genes in the context of maize subgenomes. Our results provide a quantitative understanding of the molecular processes governing the evolution of CNSs in maize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-genome-research-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://genome.cshlp.org/content/31/7/1245&quot;&gt;Genome Research (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/09/12/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/09/12/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: PAM-less plant genome editing using a CRISPR–SpRY toolbox</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rapid development of the CRISPR–Cas9, –Cas12a and – Cas12b genome editing systems has greatly fuelled basic and translational plant research1–6. DNA targeting by these Cas nucleases is restricted by their preferred protospacer adja- cent motifs (PAMs). The PAM requirement for the most popu- lar Streptococcus pyogenes Cas9 (SpCas9) is NGG (N = A, T, C, G)7, limiting its targeting scope to GC-rich regions. Here, we demonstrate genome editing at relaxed PAM sites in rice (a monocot) and the Dahurian larch (a coniferous tree), using an engineered SpRY Cas9 variant8. Highly efficient targeted mutagenesis can be readily achieved by SpRY at relaxed PAM sites in the Dahurian larch protoplasts and in rice trans- genic lines through non-homologous end joining (NHEJ). Furthermore, an SpRY-based cytosine base editor was devel- oped and demonstrated by directed evolution of new herbicide resistant OsALS alleles in rice. Similarly, a highly active SpRY adenine base editor was developed based on ABE8e (ref. 9) and SpRY-ABE8e was able to target relaxed PAM sites in rice plants, achieving up to 79% editing efficiency with high prod- uct purity. Thus, the SpRY toolbox breaks a PAM restriction barrier in plant genome engineering by enabling DNA editing in a PAM-less fashion. Evidence was also provided for second- ary off-target effects by de novo generated single guide RNAs (sgRNAs) due to SpRY-mediated transfer DNA self-editing, which calls for more sophisticated programmes for designing highly specific sgRNAs when implementing the SpRY genome editing toolbox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-plants-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41477-020-00827-4&quot;&gt;Nature Plants (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/09/06/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/09/06/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
