<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Zhang Tao lab</title>
    <description>Bioinformatics, Epigenetics and Genomics.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 22:50:36 +0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 22:50:36 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Natural polymorphism of ZmICE1 contributes to amino acid metabolism that impacts cold tolerance in maize</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cold stress negatively affects maize (Zea mays L.) growth, development and yield. Metabolic adjustments contribute to the adaptation of maize under cold stress. We show here that the transcription factor INDUCER OF CBF EXPRESSION 1 (ZmICE1) plays a prominent role in reprogramming amino acid metabolome and COLD-RESPONSIVE (COR) genes during cold stress in maize. Derivatives of amino acids glutamate/asparagine (Glu/Asn) induce a burst of mitochondrial reactive oxygen species, which suppress the cold-mediated induction of DEHYDRATION RESPONSE ELEMENT-BINDING PROTEIN 1 (ZmDREB1) genes and impair cold tolerance. ZmICE1 blocks this negative regulation of cold tolerance by directly repressing the expression of the key Glu/Asn biosynthesis genes, ASPARAGINE SYNTHETASEs. Moreover, ZmICE1 directly regulates the expression of DREB1s. Natural variation at the ZmICE1 promoter determines the binding affinity of the transcriptional activator ZmMYB39, a positive regulator of cold tolerance in maize, resulting in different degrees of ZmICE1 transcription and cold tolerance across inbred lines. This study thus unravels a mechanism of cold tolerance in maize and provides potential targets for engineering cold-tolerant varieties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-plants-2022&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41477-022-01254-3&quot;&gt;Nature Plants (2022)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/12/12/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/12/12/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A route to de novo domestication of wild allotetraploid rice</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cultivated rice varieties are all diploid, and polyploidization of rice has long been desired because of its ad- vantages in genome buffering, vigorousness, and environmental robustness. However, a workable route re- mains elusive. Here, we describe a practical strategy, namely de novo domestication of wild allotetraploid rice. By screening allotetraploid wild rice inventory, we identified one genotype of Oryza alta (CCDD), poly- ploid rice 1 (PPR1), and established two important resources for its de novo domestication: (1) an efficient tissue culture, transformation, and genome editing system and (2) a high-quality genome assembly discrim- inated into two subgenomes of 12 chromosomes apiece. With these resources, we show that six agronom- ically important traits could be rapidly improved by editing O. alta homologs of the genes controlling these traits in diploid rice. Our results demonstrate the possibility that de novo domesticated allotetraploid rice can be developed into a new staple cereal to strengthen world food security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-cell-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0092867421000131&quot;&gt;Cell (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/12/09/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/12/09/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Translatome and transcriptome co-profiling reveals a role of TPRXs in human zygotic genome activation</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Translational regulation plays a critical role during the oocyte-to-embryo transition (OET) and zygotic genome activation (ZGA). Here, we integrated ultra-low-input Ribo-seq with mRNA-seq to co-profile the translatome and transcriptome in human oocytes and early embryos. Comparison with mouse counterparts identified widespread differentially translated genes functioning in epigenetic reprogramming, transposon defense, and small RNA biogenesis, in part driven by species-specific regulatory elements in 3′ untranslated regions. Moreover, PRD-like homeobox transcription factors, including TPRXL, TPRX1, and TPRX2, are highly translated around ZGA. TPRX1/2/L knockdown leads to defective ZGA and preimplantation development. Ectopically expressed TPRXs bind and activate key ZGA genes in human embryonic stem cells. These data reveal the conservation and divergence of translation landscapes during OET and identify critical regulators of human ZGA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-science-2022&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.abo7923&quot;&gt;Science (2022)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/09/16/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/09/16/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Inactivation of rice starch branching enzyme IIb triggers broad and unexpected changes in metabolism by transcriptional reprogramming</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starch properties can be modified by mutating genes responsible for the synthesis of amylose and amylopectin in the endosperm. How- ever, little is known about the effects of such targeted modifications on the overall starch biosynthesis pathway and broader metabolism. Here we investigated the effects of mutating the OsSBEIIb gene encoding starch branching enzyme IIb, which is required for amylo- pectin synthesis in the endosperm. As anticipated, homozygous mu- tant plants, in which OsSBEIIb was completely inactivated by abolishing the catalytic center and C-terminal regulatory domain, pro- duced opaque seeds with depleted starch reserves. Amylose content in the mutant increased from 19.6 to 27.4% and resistant starch (RS) content increased from 0.2 to 17.2%. Many genes encoding isoforms of AGPase, soluble starch synthase, and other starch branching en- zymes were up-regulated, either in their native tissues or in an ectopic manner, whereas genes encoding granule-bound starch synthase, debranching enzymes, pullulanase, and starch phosphorylases were largely down-regulated. There was a general increase in the accumu- lation of sugars, fatty acids, amino acids, and phytosterols in the mu- tant endosperm, suggesting that intermediates in the starch biosynthesis pathway increased flux through spillover pathways causing a profound impact on the accumulation of multiple primary and secondary metabolites. Our results provide insights into the broader implications of perturbing starch metabolism in rice endo- sperm and its impact on the whole plant, which will make it easier to predict the effect of metabolic engineering in cereals for nutritional improvement or the production of valuable metabolites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-pnas-2020&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/doi/suppl/10.1073/pnas.2014860117&quot;&gt;PNAS (2020)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/09/12/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/09/12/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Pan-brassinosteroid signaling revealed by functional analysis of NILR1 in land plants</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brassinosteroid (BR) signaling has been identified from the ligand BRs sensed by the receptor Brassinosteroid Insensitive 1 (BRI1) to the final activation of Brassinozole Resistant 1/bri1 EMS-Suppressor 1 through a series of transduction events. Extensive studies have been conducted to characterize the role of BR signaling in various biological processes. Our previous study has shown that Excess Microsporocytes 1 (EMS1) and BRI1 control different aspects of plant growth and development via conserved intracellular signaling.
Here, we reveal that another receptor, NILR1, can complement the bri1 mutant in the absence of BRs, indicating a pathway that resembles BR signaling activated by NILR1. Genetic analysis confirms the intracellular domains of NILR1, BRI1 and EMS1 have a common signal output.
Furthermore, we demonstrate that NILR1 and BRI1 share the coreceptor BRI1 Associated Kinase 1 and substrate BSKs. Notably, the NILR1-mediated downstream pathway is conserved across land plants.
In summary, we provide evidence for the signaling cascade of NILR1, suggesting pan-brassinosteroid signaling initiated by a group of distant receptor–ligand pairs in land plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-new-phytologist-2022&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://nph.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/nph.18228&quot;&gt;New Phytologist (2022)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/08/26/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/08/26/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Modeling temporal and hormonal regulation of plant transcriptional response to wounding</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plants respond to wounding stress by changing gene expression patterns and inducing the production of hormones including jasmonic acid. This wounding transcriptional response activates specialized metabolism pathways such as the glucosinolate pathways in Arabidopsis thaliana. While the regulatory factors and sequences controlling a subset of wound-response genes are known, it remains unclear how wound response is regulated globally. Here, we how these responses are regulated by incorporating putative cis-regulatory elements, known transcription factor binding sites, in vitro DNA affinity purification sequencing, and DNase I hypersensitive sites to predict genes with different wound-response patterns using machine learning. We observed that regulatory sites and regions of open chromatin differed between genes upregulated at early and late wounding time-points as well as between genes induced by jasmonic acid and those not induced. Expanding on what we currently know, we identified cis-elements that improved model predictions of expression clusters over known binding sites. Using a combination of genome editing, in vitro DNA-binding assays, and transient expression assays using native and mutated cis-regulatory elements, we experimentally validated four of the predicted elements, three of which were not previously known to function in wound-response regulation. Our study provides a global model predictive of wound response and identifies new regulatory sequences important for wounding without requiring prior knowledge of the transcriptional regulators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-the-plant-cell-2022&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/plcell/article/34/2/867/6448773&quot;&gt;the Plant Cell (2022)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/07/29/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/07/29/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Genome-wide cis-decoding for expression design in tomato using cistrome data and explainable deep learning</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the evolutionary history of plants, variation in cis-regulatory elements (CREs) resulting in diversification of gene expression has played a central role in driving the evolution of lineage-specific traits. However, it is difficult to predict expression behaviors from CRE patterns to properly harness them, mainly because the biological processes are complex. In this study, we used cistrome datasets and explainable convolutional neural network (CNN) frameworks to predict genome-wide expression patterns in tomato (Solanum lycopersicum) fruit from the DNA sequences in gene regulatory regions. By fixing the effects of trans-acting factors using single cell-type spatiotemporal transcriptome data for the response variables, we developed a prediction model for crucial expression patterns in the initiation of tomato fruit ripening. Feature visualization of the CNNs identified nucleotide residues critical to the objective expression pattern in each gene, and their effects were validated experimentally in ripening tomato fruit. This cis-decoding framework will not only contribute to the understanding of the regulatory networks derived from CREs and transcription factor interactions, but also provides a flexible means of designing alleles for optimized expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-the-plant-cell-2022&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/plcell/article/34/6/2174/6542321&quot;&gt;the Plant Cell (2022)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/07/17/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/07/17/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>OsAAP6 functions as an important regulator of grain protein content and nutritional quality in rice</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grains from cereals contribute an important source of protein to human food, and grain protein content (GPC) is an important determinant of nutritional quality in cereals. Here we show that the quantitative trait locus (QTL) qPC1 in rice controls GPC by regulating the synthesis and accumulation of glutelins, prolamins, globulins, albumins and starch. qPC1 encodes a putative amino acid transporter OsAAP6, which functions as a positive regulator of GPC in rice, such that higher expression of OsAAP6 is correlated with higher GPC. OsAAP6 greatly enhances root absorption of a range of amino acids and has effects on the distribution of various amino acids. Two common variations in the potential cis-regulatory elements of the OsAAP6 5′-untranslated region seem to be associated with GPC diversity mainly in indica cultivars. Our results represent the first step toward unravelling the mechanism of regulation underlying natural variation of GPC in rice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-communications-2014&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/ncomms5847&quot;&gt;Nature Communications (2014)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/06/29/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/06/29/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>H1 linker histones silence repetitive elements by promoting both histone H3K9 methylation and chromatin compaction</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly 50% of mouse and human genomes are composed of repetitive sequences. Transcription of these sequences is tightly controlled during development to prevent genomic instability, inappropriate gene activation and other maladaptive processes. Here, we demonstrate an integral role for H1 linker histones in silencing repetitive elements in mouse embryonic stem cells. Strong H1 depletion causes a profound de-repression of several classes of repetitive sequences, including major satellite, LINE-1, and ERV. Activation of repetitive sequence transcription is accompanied by decreased H3K9 trimethylation of repetitive sequence chromatin. H1 linker histones interact directly with Suv39h1, Suv39h2, and SETDB1, the histone methyltransferases responsible for H3K9 trimethylation of chromatin within these regions, and stimulate their activity toward chromatin in vitro. However, we also implicate chromatin compaction mediated by H1 as an additional, dominant repressive mechanism for silencing of repetitive major satellite sequences. Our findings elucidate two distinct, H1-mediated pathways for silencing heterochromatin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-pnas-2020&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/doi/suppl/10.1073/pnas.1920725117&quot;&gt;PNAS (2020)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/06/22/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/06/22/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Splicing-mediated activation of SHAGGY-like kinases underpinning carbon partitioning in Arabidopsis seeds</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Glycogen synthase kinase 3 (GSK3) family members serve as signaling hubs for plant development and stress responses, yet the underlying mechanism of their transcriptional regulation remains a long-standing mystery. Here we show that the tran- scription of SHAGGY-like kinase 11/12 (SK11/12), two members of the GSK3 gene family, is promoted by the splicing factor SmD1b, which is essential for distributing carbon sources into storage and protective components in Arabidopsis seeds. The chromatin recruitment of SmD1b at the SK11/12 loci promotes their transcription associated with co-transcriptional splicing of the first introns in the 50-untranslated region of SK11/12. The loss of SmD1b function generates transcripts with unspliced introns that create disruptive R-loops to hamper the transcriptional elongation of SK11/12, in addition to compromising the recruitment of RNA polymerase II to the SK11/12 genomic regions. These effects imposed by SmD1b de- termine the transcription of SK11/12 to confer a key switch of carbon flow among metabolic pathways in zygotic and ma- ternal tissues in seeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-the-plant-cell-2022&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/plcell/advance-article-abstract/doi/10.1093/plcell/koac110/6569842?redirectedFrom=fulltext&quot;&gt;the Plant Cell (2022)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2022/06/14/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2022/06/14/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
