<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Zhang Tao lab</title>
    <description>Bioinformatics, Epigenetics and Genomics.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 00:24:28 +0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 00:24:28 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: The key role of terminators on the expression and post- transcriptional gene silencing of transgenes</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transgenes have become essential to modern biology, being an important tool in functional genomic studies and also in the development of biotechnological products. One of the major challenges in the generation of transgenic lines concerns the expression of transgenes, which, compared to endogenes, are particularly susceptible to silencing mediated by small RNAs (sRNAs). Several reasons have been put forward to explain why transgenes often trigger the production of sRNAs, such as the high level of expression induced by commonly used strong constitutive promoters, the lack of introns, and features resembling viral and other exogenous sequences. However, the relative contributions of the different genomic elements with respect to protecting genes from the silencing machinery and their molecular mechanisms remain unclear. Here, we present the results of a mutagenesis screen conceived to identify features involved in the protection of endogenes against becoming a template for the production of sRNAs. Interestingly, all of the recovered mutants had alterations in genes with proposed function in transcription termination, suggesting a central role of terminators in this process. Indeed, using a GFP reporter system, we show that, among different genetic elements tested, the terminator sequence had the greatest effect on transgene-derived sRNA accumulation and that a well-defined poly(A) site might be especially important. Finally, we describe an unexpected mechanism, where transgenes containing certain intron/terminator combinations lead to an increase in the production of sRNAs, which appears to interfere with splicing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-the-plant-journal-2020&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/tpj.14907&quot;&gt;The Plant Journal (2020)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/08/29/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/08/29/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: KOBAS-i: intelligent prioritization and exploratory visualization of biological functions for gene enrichment analysis</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gene set enrichment (GSE) analysis plays an essen- tial role in extracting biological insight from genome- scale experiments. ORA (overrepresentation analy- sis), FCS (functional class scoring), and PT (path- way topology) approaches are three generations of GSE methods along the timeline of development. Pre- vious versions of KOBAS provided services based on just the ORA method. Here we presented ver- sion 3.0 of KOBAS, which is named KOBAS-i (short for KOBAS intelligent version). It introduced a novel machine learning-based method we published ear- lier, CGPS, which incorporates seven FCS tools and two PT tools into a single ensemble score and in- telligently prioritizes the relevant biological path- ways. In addition, KOBAS has expanded the down- stream exploratory visualization for selecting and understanding the enriched results. The tool con- structs a novel view of cirFunMap, which presents different enriched terms and their correlations in a landscape. Finally, based on the previous version’s framework, KOBAS increased the number of sup- ported species from 1327 to 5944. For an easier lo- cal run, it also provides a prebuilt Docker image that requires no installation, as a supplementary to the source code version. KOBAS can be freely accessed at http://kobas.cbi.pku.edu.cn, and a mirror site is available at http://bioinfo.org/kobas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nucleic-acids-research-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/nar/article/49/W1/W317/6292104&quot;&gt;Nucleic Acids Research (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/08/01/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/08/01/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Integrated global analysis reveals a vitamin E- vitamin K1 sub-network, downstream of COLD1, underlying rice chilling tolerance divergence</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rice, a staple food with tropical/subtropical origination, is susceptible to cold stress, one of the major con- straints on its yield and distribution. Asian cultivated rice consists of two subspecies with diverged chilling tolerance to adapt to different environments. The mechanism underlying this divergence remains obscure with a few known factors, including membrane protein CHILLING-TOLERANCE DIVERGENCE 1 (COLD1). Here, we reveal a vitamin E-vitamin K1 sub-network responsible for chilling tolerance divergence through global analyses. Rice genome regions responsible for tolerance divergence are identified with chromosome segment substitution lines (CSSLs). Comparative transcriptomic and metabolomic analysis of chilling- tolerant CSSL4-1 and parent lines uncovered a vitamin E-vitamin K1 sub-network in chloroplast with tocoph- erol (vitamin E) mediating chloroplast-to-nucleus signaling. COLD1, located in the substitution segment in CSSL4-1, is confirmed as its upstream regulator by transgenic material analysis. Our work uncovers a pathway downstream of COLD1, through which rice modulates chilling tolerance for thermal adaptation, with potential utility in crop improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-cell-reports-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cell.com/cell-reports/fulltext/S2211-1247(21)00795-6&quot;&gt;Cell Reports (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/07/26/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/07/26/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: The Taxus genome provides insights into paclitaxel biosynthesis</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ancient gymnosperm genus Taxus is the exclusive source of the anticancer drug paclitaxel, yet no reference genome sequences are available for comprehensively elucidating the paclitaxel biosynthesis pathway. We have completed a chromosome-level genome of Taxus chinensis var. mairei with a total length of 10.23 gigabases. Taxus shared an ancestral whole-genome duplication with the coniferophyte lineage and underwent distinct transposon evolution. We discovered a unique physical and functional grouping of CYP725As (cytochrome P450) in the Taxus genome for paclitaxel biosynthesis. We also identified a gene cluster for taxadiene biosynthesis, which was formed mainly by gene duplications. This study will facilitate the elucidation of paclitaxel biosynthesis and unleash the biotechnological potential of Taxus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-plants-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41477-021-00963-5&quot;&gt;Nature Plants (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/07/18/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/07/18/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: In vivo nuclear RNA structurome reveals RNA-structure regulation of mRNA processing in plants</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background:&lt;/strong&gt; mRNA processing is critical for gene expression. A challenge in regulating mRNA processing is how to recognize the actual mRNA processing sites, such as splice and polyadenylation sites, when the sequence content is insufficient for this purpose. Previous studies suggested that RNA structure affects mRNA processing. However, the regulatory role of RNA structure in mRNA processing remains unclear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results:&lt;/strong&gt; Here, we perform in vivo selective 2′-hydroxyl acylation analyzed by primer extension (SHAPE) chemical profiling on Arabidopsis and generate the in vivo nuclear RNA structure landscape. We find that nuclear mRNAs fold differently from cytosolic mRNAs across translation start and stop sites. Notably, we discover a two-nucleotide single-stranded RNA structure feature upstream of 5′ splice sites that is strongly associated with splicing and the selection of alternative 5′ splice sites. The regulatory role of this RNA structure feature is further confirmed by experimental validation. Moreover, we find the single-strandedness of branch sites is also associated with 3′ splice site recognition. We also identify an RNA structure feature comprising two close-by single-stranded regions that is specifically associated with both polyadenylation and alternative polyadenylation events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions:&lt;/strong&gt; We successfully identify pre-mRNA structure features associated with splicing and polyadenylation at whole-genome scale and validate an RNA structure feature which can regulate splicing. Our study unveils a new RNA structure regulatory mechanism for mRNA processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-genome-biology-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13059-020-02236-4&quot;&gt;Genome Biology (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/07/13/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/07/13/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Determinants of genome-wide distribution and evolution of uORFs in eukaryotes</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upstream open reading frames (uORFs) play widespread regulatory functions in modulating mRNA translation in eukaryotes, but the principles underlying the genomic distribution and evolution of uORFs remain poorly understood. Here, we analyze ~17 million putative canonical uORFs in 478 eukaryotic species that span most of the extant taxa of eukaryotes. We demonstrate how positive and purifying selection, coupled with differences in effective population size (Ne), has shaped the contents of uORFs in eukaryotes. Besides, gene expression level is important in influencing uORF occurrences across genes in a species. Our analyses suggest that most uORFs might play regulatory roles rather than encode functional peptides. We also show that the Kozak sequence context of uORFs has evolved across eukaryotic clades, and that noncanonical uORFs tend to have weaker suppressive effects than canonical uORFs in translation regulation. This study provides insights into the driving forces underlying uORF evolution in eukaryotes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-communications-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-021-21394-y&quot;&gt;Nature Communications (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/07/04/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/07/04/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Chromatin Landscape Underpinning Human Dendritic Cell Heterogeneity</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human dendritic cells (DCs) comprise subsets with distinct phenotypic and functional characteristics, but the transcriptional programs that dictate their identity remain elusive. Here, we analyze global chromatin acces- sibility profiles across resting and stimulated human DC subsets by means of the assay for transposase- accessible chromatin using sequencing (ATAC-seq). We uncover specific regions of chromatin accessibility for each subset and transcriptional regulators of DC function. By comparing plasmacytoid DC responses to IFN-I-producing and non-IFN-I-producing conditions, we identify genetic programs related to their function. Finally, by intersecting chromatin accessibility with genome-wide association studies, we recognize DC subset-specific enrichment of heritability in autoimmune diseases. Our results unravel the basis of human DC subset heterogeneity and provide a framework for their analysis in disease pathogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-cell-reports-2020&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cell.com/cell-reports/fulltext/S2211-1247(20)31169-4&quot;&gt;Cell Reports (2020)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/06/20/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/06/20/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Natural variations of SLG1 confer high-temperature tolerance in indica rice</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With global warming and climate change, breeding crop plants tolerant to high-temperature stress is of immense significance. tRNA 2-thiolation is a highly conserved form of tRNA modification among living organisms. Here, we report the identification of SLG1 (Slender Guy 1), which encodes the cytosolic tRNA 2-thiolation protein 2 (RCTU2) in rice. SLG1 plays a key role in the response of rice plants to high-temperature stress at both seedling and reproductive stages. Dysfunction of SLG1 results in plants with thermosensitive phenotype, while overexpression of SLG1 enhances the tolerance of plants to high temperature. SLG1 is differentiated between the two Asian cultivated rice subspecies, indica and japonica, and the variations at both promoter and coding regions lead to an increased level of thiolated tRNA and enhanced thermotolerance of indica rice varieties. Our results demonstrate that the allelic differentiation of SLG1 confers indica rice to high-temperature tolerance, and tRNA thiolation pathway might be a potential target in the next generation rice breeding for the warming globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-communication-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-020-19320-9&quot;&gt;Nature Communication (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/06/13/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/06/13/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Single-nucleotide-level mapping of DNA regulatory elements that control fetal hemoglobin expression</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pinpointing functional noncoding DNA sequences and defining their contributions to health-related traits is a major challenge for modern genetics. We developed a high-throughput framework to map noncoding DNA functions with single-nucleotide resolution in four loci that control erythroid fetal hemoglobin (HbF) expression, a genetically determined trait that modifies sickle cell disease (SCD) phenotypes. Specifically, we used the adenine base editor ABEmax to introduce 10,156 separate A•T to G•C conversions in 307 predicted regulatory elements and quantified the effects on erythroid HbF expression. We identified numerous regulatory elements, defined their epigenomic structures and linked them to low-frequency variants associated with HbF expression in an SCD cohort. Targeting a newly discovered γ-globin gene repressor element in SCD donor CD34+ hematopoietic progenitors raised HbF levels in the erythroid progeny, inhibiting hypoxia-induced sickling. Our findings reveal previously unappreciated genetic complexities of HbF regulation and provide potentially therapeutic insights into SCD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-genetics-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41588-021-00861-8&quot;&gt;Nature Genetics (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/05/30/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/05/30/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Chromothripsis as an on-target consequence of CRISPR–Cas9 genome editing</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genome editing has therapeutic potential for treating genetic diseases and cancer. However, the currently most practicable approaches rely on the generation of DNA double-strand breaks (DSBs), which can give rise to a poorly characterized spectrum of chromosome structural abnormalities. Here, using model cells and single-cell whole-genome sequencing, as well as by editing at a clinically relevant locus in clinically relevant cells, we show that CRISPR–Cas9 editing generates structural defects of the nucleus, micronuclei and chromosome bridges, which initiate a mutational process called chromothripsis. Chromothripsis is extensive chromosome rearrangement restricted to one or a few chromosomes that can cause human congenital disease and cancer. These results demonstrate that chromothripsis is a previously unappreciated on-target consequence of CRISPR–Cas9-generated DSBs. As genome editing is implemented in the clinic, the potential for extensive chromosomal rearrangements should be considered and monitored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-genetics-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41588-021-00838-7&quot;&gt;Nature Genetics (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 23 May 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/05/23/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/05/23/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
