<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Zhang Tao lab</title>
    <description>Bioinformatics, Epigenetics and Genomics.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 11 Apr 2021 10:31:28 +0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Apr 2021 10:31:28 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Molecular Networks of Seed Size Control in Plants</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The size of seeds affects not only evolutionary fitness but also grain yield of crops. Understanding the mechanisms controlling seed size has become an important research field in plant science. Seed size is determined by the integrated signals of maternal and zygotic tissues, which control the coordinated growth of the embryo, endosperm, and seed coat. Recent advances have identified several signaling pathways that control seed size through maternal tissues, including or involving the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway, G-protein signaling, mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) signaling, phytohormone perception and homeostasis, and some transcriptional regulators. Meanwhile, growth of the zygotic tissues is regulated in part by the HAIKU (IKU) pathway and phytohormones. This review provides a general overview of current findings in seed size control and discusses the emerging molecular mechanisms and regulatory networks found to be involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-annual-review-of-plant-biology-2019&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.annualreviews.org/doi/10.1146/annurev-arplant-050718-095851&quot;&gt;Annual Review of Plant Biology (2019)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/04/11/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/04/11/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Identification of Plant Enhancers and Their Constituent Elements by STARR-seq in Tobacco Leaves</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genetic engineering of cis-regulatory elements in crop plants is a promising strategy to ensure food security. However, such engineering is currently hindered by our limited knowledge of plant cis-regulatory elements. Here, we adapted self-transcribing active regulatory region sequencing (STARR-seq)—a technology for the high-throughput identification of enhancers—for its use in transiently transformed tobacco (Nicotiana benthamiana) leaves. We demonstrate that the optimal placement in the reporter construct of enhancer sequences from a plant virus, pea (Pisum sativum) and wheat (Triticum aestivum), was just upstream of a minimal promoter and that none of these four known enhancers was active in the 39 untranslated region of the reporter gene. The optimized assay sensitively identified small DNA regions containing each of the four enhancers, including two whose activity was stimulated by light. Furthermore, we coupled the assay to saturation mutagenesis to pinpoint functional regions within an enhancer, which we recombined to create synthetic enhancers. Our results describe an approach to define enhancer properties that can be performed in potentially any plant species or tissue transformable by Agrobacterium and that can use regulatory DNA derived from any plant genome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-the-plant-cell-2020&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/plcell/article/32/7/2120/6115620&quot;&gt;The Plant Cell (2020)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 04 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/04/04/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/04/04/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Epigenetic reprogramming rewires transcription during the alternation of generations in Arabidopsis</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternation between morphologically distinct haploid and diploid life forms is a defining feature of most plant and algal life cycles, yet the underlying molecular mechanisms that govern these transitions remain unclear. Here, we explore the dynamic relationship between chromatin accessibility and epigenetic modifications during life form transitions in Arabidopsis. The diploid-to-haploid life form transition is governed by the loss of H3K9me2 and DNA demethylation of transposon-associated cis-regulatory elements. This event is associated with dramatic changes in chromatin accessibility and transcriptional reprogramming. In contrast, the global loss of H3K27me3 in the haploid form shapes a chromatin accessibility landscape that is poised to re-initiate the transition back to diploid life after fertilisation. Hence, distinct epigenetic reprogramming events rewire transcription through major reorganisation of the regulatory epigenome to guide the alternation of generations in flowering plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-elife-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://elifesciences.org/articles/61894&quot;&gt;eLife (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/03/20/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/03/20/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Chromatin Accessibility Dynamics and a Hierarchical Transcriptional Regulatory Network Structure for Plant Somatic Embryogenesis</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plant somatic embryogenesis refers to a phenomenon where embryos develop from somatic cells in the absence of fertilization. Previous studies have revealed that the phytohormone auxin plays a crucial role in somatic embryogenesis by inducing a cell totipotent state, although its underlying mechanism is poorly understood. Here, we show that auxin rapidly rewires the cell totipotency network by altering chromatin accessibility. The analysis of chromatin accessibility dynamics further reveals a hierarchical gene regulatory network underlying somatic embryogenesis. Particularly, we find that the embryonic nature of explants is a prerequisite for somatic cell reprogramming. Upon cell reprogramming, the B3-type totipotent transcription factor LEC2 promotes somatic embryo formation by direct activation of the early embryonic patterning genes WOX2 and WOX3. Our results thus shed light on the molecular mechanism by which auxin promotes the acquisition of plant cell totipotency and establish a direct link between cell totipotent genes and the embryonic development pathway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-developmental-cell-2020&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S1534580720305517&quot;&gt;Developmental Cell (2020)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 13 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/03/13/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/03/13/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: The relationship between genome structure and function</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Precise patterns of gene expression in metazoans are controlled by three classes of regulatory elements: promoters, enhancers and boundary elements. During differentiation and development, these elements form specific interactions in dynamic higher-order chromatin structures. However, the relationship between genome structure and its function in gene regulation is not completely understood. Here we review recent progress in this field and discuss whether genome structure plays an instructive role in regulating gene expression or is a reflection of the activity of the regulatory elements of the genome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-reviews-genetics-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41576-020-00303-x#author-information&quot;&gt;Nature Reviews Genetics (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/03/06/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/03/06/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Chorus2 oligo datasets</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Oligo datasets which host oligo sequences for Oligo-FISH.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/download/oligo_datasets&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Details&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The oligo datasets currently host oligo sequences of nine species, including Arabidopsis, rice, maize, potato, barley, soybean, human, mouse and zebrafish. All the oligos are designed by Chorus2 software.&lt;br /&gt;
The details of the datasets are shown &lt;a href=&quot;/database/oligo_datasets&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/info/download/oligo_datasets</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/info/download/oligo_datasets</guid>
        
        
        <category>download</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>PlantDHS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;PlantDHS: a database for DNase I hypersensitive sites (DHSs) in plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://plantdhs.org/&quot;&gt;Go to&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PlantDHS&lt;/strong&gt; is a plant DNase I hypersensitive site (DHS) database that integrates histone modification, RNA sequencing, nucleosome positioning/occupancy, transcription factor binding sites (TFBS), and genomic sequence within an easily navigated user interface. DHSs are indicative of all CREs, including promoters, enhancers, silencers, insulators and transcription factor binding sites.&lt;br /&gt;
PlantDHS provides a platform to predict all CREs associated with individual genes from three model plant species, including &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Brachypodium distachyon&lt;/em&gt; and rice (&lt;em&gt;Oryza sativa&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zhang T, Marand A, Jiang JM*. &lt;a href=&quot;http://zhangtaolab.org/pdf/2016/NAR_2016.pdf&quot;&gt;PlantDHS: A Database for DNase I Hypertensive Sites in Plants.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nucleic Acids Research&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; 2016, 44(D1):D1148-D1153.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;preview&quot;&gt;Preview&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/PlantDHS/Figure1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/PlantDHS/Figure2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/info/database/plantdhs</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/info/database/plantdhs</guid>
        
        
        <category>database</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Popera</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A software specially designed for DHS identification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/forrestzhang/Popera&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Github&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DNase I hypersensitive sites (DHSs) are regions of chromatin that are sensitive to cleavage by the DNase I enzyme. In these specific regions of the genome, chromatin has lost its condensed structure, exposing the DNA and making it accessible.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Popera&lt;/strong&gt; is specially designed for identifying genome-wide DHSs from DNase-seq reads. First, Popera identifies the DHSs by applying the kernel density estimation algorithm. Second, all the DHSs identified from various tissues and developmental stages were merged to create a unified DHS file; DHSs were then assigned unique ID tags. Lastly, normalized scores of unified DHSs were calculated for each unique tissue and developmental stage. Besides, Popera can generate smooth bigwig files, which provide more explicit and pretty visualization for downstream analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;preview&quot;&gt;Preview&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DHS identified by &lt;em&gt;Popera&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Popera/DHS_Popera.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2000 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/software/popera</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/software/popera</guid>
        
        
        <category>software</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>CRISPR-BETS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A gRNA design software for base editing knockout using stop codon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bioinfor.yzu.edu.cn/crisprbets/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/yuechaowu/CRISPR-BETS_desktop&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Desktop&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Documentation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CRISPR-BETS&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;CRISPR&lt;/strong&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;ase &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt;diting &lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;o &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt;top codon) is developed for designing gRNA to knockout gene by CRISPR base editing system. CRISPR-BETS has both online and desktop version, which are integrated into a user-friendly graphic user interface (GUI) and compatible with major operating systems (Windows, MacOS, Linux). Guide RNAs can be designed easily without any environment installation. Users can complete the analysis with a simple mouse click. Results will display with detailed information and fancy images, which are able to be downloaded. Moreover, CRISPR-BETS allows instant check the gRNA specificity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;preview&quot;&gt;Preview&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/CRISPR-BETS/CRISPR-BETS_preview01.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/CRISPR-BETS/CRISPR-BETS_preview02.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2000 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/software/crisprbets</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/software/crisprbets</guid>
        
        
        <category>software</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Chorus2</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Design of genome-scale oligonucleotide-based probes for fluorescence &lt;em&gt;in situ&lt;/em&gt; hybridization (FISH)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/zhangtaolab/Chorus2/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GitHub&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://chorus2.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Documentation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chorus2&lt;/strong&gt;, a software that is developed specifically for oligo selection in plant species. It is highly effective to remove all repetitive elements in selection of single copy oligos, which is critical for the development of successful FISH probes. Chorus2 is more effective than Chorus and OligoMiner for repeat removal. Chorus2 allows to select oligos that are conserved among related species, which extends the usage of oligo-FISH probes among phylogenetically related plant species. Chorus2 allows development of FISH probes from plant species without an assembled genome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;video-tutorials&quot;&gt;Video tutorials&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLo8q8tqFX5J27OsuKYFpd-gOtl8Qgf70X&quot;&gt;YouTube (EN)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bilibili.com/video/BV1W54y1S7qS/&quot;&gt;bilibili (中文)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;oligo-design-with-choruschorus2&quot;&gt;Oligo design with Chorus/Chorus2&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wheat&lt;/strong&gt;: Li GR†, Zhang T†, Yu ZH, Wang HJ, Yang EN, Yang ZJ*. &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/tpj.15081&quot;&gt;An efficient Oligo‐FISH painting system for revealing chromosome rearrangements and polyploidization in Triticeae.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Plant Journal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; 2021, 105(4):978-993&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rice&lt;/strong&gt;: Liu XY†, Sun S†, Wu Y, Zhou Y, Gu S.W, Yu H.X, Yi CD, Gu MH, Jiang JM, Liu B, Zhang T*, Gong ZY*. &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/tpj.14522&quot;&gt;Dual‐color oligo‐FISH can reveal chromosomal variations and evolution in Oryza species.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Plant Journal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; 2020, 101:112-121&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maize&lt;/strong&gt;: Albert P.S†, Zhang T†, Semrau K, Rouillard JM, Kao YH, Wang CJ, Danilova T.V, Jiang JM, and Birchler J*. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/116/5/1679&quot;&gt;Whole-chromosome paints in maize reveal rearrangements, nuclear domains, and chromosomal relationships&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; 2019, 16(5):1679-1685&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Populus&lt;/strong&gt;: Xin HY†, Zhang T†, Wu YF, Zhang WL, Zhang PD, Xi ML*, Jiang JM. &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/epdf/10.1111/tpj.14536&quot;&gt;An extraordinarily stable karyotype of the woody Populus species revealed by chromosome painting.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Plant Journal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; 2020, 101:253-264&lt;br /&gt;
Xin H†, Zhang T†, Han Y, Wu YF, Shi JS, Xi ML*, and Jiang JM. &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00412-018-0664-y&quot;&gt;Chromosome painting and comparative physical mapping of the sex chromosomes in Populus tomentosa and Populus deltoides.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Chromosoma&lt;/em&gt; 2018, 127(3):313-321&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Potato&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Tomato&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Eggplant&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Tzimbalo&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Pepper&lt;/strong&gt;: Braz GT†, He L†, Zhao HN†, Zhang T†, Semrau K, Rouillard JM, Torres GA, Jiang JM*. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.genetics.org/content/208/2/513.full.pdf&quot;&gt;Comparative oligo-FISH mapping: an efficient and powerful methodology to reveal karyotypic and chromosomal evolution.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Genetics&lt;/em&gt; 2018, 208(2):513-523&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cucumber&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Muskmelon&lt;/strong&gt; and other &lt;strong&gt;Cucumis&lt;/strong&gt;: Han YH†, Zhang T†, Thammapichai P, Weng YQ, and Jiang JM*:  &lt;a href=&quot;/pdf/2015/Genetics_2015.pdf&quot;&gt;Chromosome-specific painting in Cucumis species using bulked oligonucleotides.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Genetics&lt;/em&gt; 2015, 200(3):771-779&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cotton, Switchgrass, Sugarcane, Banana and etc …&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;oligo-fish-performed-with-choruschorus2-designed-probes&quot;&gt;Oligo-FISH performed with Chorus/Chorus2 designed probes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Chorus2/F1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Chorus2/F2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Chorus2/F3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Chorus2/F4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;oligo-database&quot;&gt;Oligo database&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have developed an oligo database for several plant species. The database currently covers six popular plant species.&lt;br /&gt;
The oligo database is available &lt;a href=&quot;http://192.168.127.25:4000/database/oligo_database&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2000 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/software/chorus2</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/software/chorus2</guid>
        
        
        <category>software</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
