<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Zhang Tao lab</title>
    <description>Bioinformatics, Epigenetics and Genomics.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 09:23:02 +0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 09:23:02 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: MAC5, an RNA-binding protein, protects pri-miRNAs from SERRATE-dependent exoribonuclease activities</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MAC5 is a component of the conserved MOS4-associated complex. It plays critical roles in development and immunity. Here we report that MAC5 is required for microRNA (miRNA) biogenesis. MAC5 interacts with Serrate (SE), which is a core component of the microprocessor that processes primary miRNA transcripts (pri-miRNAs) into miRNAs and binds the stem-loop region of pri-miRNAs. MAC5 is essential for both the efficient processing and the stability of pri-miRNAs. Interestingly, the reduction of pri-miRNA levels in &lt;em&gt;mac5&lt;/em&gt; is partially caused by XRN2/XRN3, the nuclear-localized 5′-to-3′ exoribonucleases, and depends on SE. These results reveal that MAC5 plays a dual role in promoting pri-miRNA processing and stability through its interaction with SE and/or pri-miRNAs. This study also uncovers that pri-miRNAs need to be protected from nuclear RNA decay machinery, which is connected to the microprocessor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-pnas-2020&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/117/38/23982&quot;&gt;PNAS (2020)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/10/18/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/10/18/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Determinants of genome-wide distribution and evolution of uORFs in eukaryotes</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upstream open reading frames (uORFs) play widespread regulatory functions in modulating mRNA translation in eukaryotes, but the principles underlying the genomic distribution and evolution of uORFs remain poorly understood. Here, we analyze ~17 million putative canonical uORFs in 478 eukaryotic species that span most of the extant taxa of eukaryotes. We demonstrate how positive and purifying selection, coupled with differences in effective population size (Ne), has shaped the contents of uORFs in eukaryotes. Besides, gene expression level is important in influencing uORF occurrences across genes in a species. Our analyses suggest that most uORFs might play regulatory roles rather than encode functional peptides. We also show that the Kozak sequence context of uORFs has evolved across eukaryotic clades, and that noncanonical uORFs tend to have weaker suppressive effects than canonical uORFs in translation regulation. This study provides insights into the driving forces underlying uORF evolution in eukaryotes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-communications-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-021-21394-y&quot;&gt;Nature Communications (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/10/10/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/10/10/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Analysis of gene network bifurcation during optic cup morphogenesis in zebrafish</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sight depends on the tight cooperation between photoreceptors and pigmented cells, which derive from common progenitors through the bifurcation of a single gene regulatory network into the neural retina (NR) and retinal-pigmented epithelium (RPE) programs. Although genetic studies have identified upstream nodes controlling these networks, their regulatory logic remains poorly investigated. Here, we characterize transcriptome dynamics and chromatin accessibility in segregating NR/RPE populations in zebrafish. We analyze cis-regulatory modules and enriched transcription factor motives to show extensive network redundancy and context-dependent activity. We identify downstream targets, highlighting an early recruitment of desmosomal genes in the flattening RPE and revealing Tead factors as upstream regulators. We investigate the RPE specification network dynamics to uncover an unexpected sequence of transcription factors recruitment, which is conserved in humans. This systematic interrogation of the NR/RPE bifurcation should improve both genetic counseling for eye disorders and hiPSCs-to-RPE differentiation protocols for cell-replacement therapies in degenerative diseases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-communications-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-021-24169-7&quot;&gt;Nature Communications (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/09/27/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/09/27/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: RGN1 controls grain number and shapes panicle architecture in rice</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yield in rice is determined mainly by panicle architecture. Using map-based cloning we identified an R2R3 MYB transcription factor REGULATOR OF GRAIN NUMBER1 (RGN1) affecting grain number and panicle architecture. Mutation of RGN1 caused an absence of lateral grains on secondary branches. We demonstrated that RGN1 controls lateral grain formation by regulation of LONELY GUY (LOG) expression, thus controlling grain number and shaping panicle architecture. A novel favorable allele, RGN1C, derived from the Or-I group in wild rice affected panicle architecture by means longer panicles. Identification of RGN1 provides a theoretical basis for understanding the molecular mechanism of lateral grain formation in rice, RGN1 will be an important gene resource for molecular breeding for higher yield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-plant-biotechnology-journal-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://genome.cshlp.org/content/31/7/1245&quot;&gt;Plant Biotechnology Journal (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/09/19/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/09/19/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Conserved noncoding sequences provide insights into regulatory sequence and loss of gene expression in maize</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thousands of species will be sequenced in the next few years; however, understanding how their genomes work, without an unlimited budget, requires both molecular and novel evolutionary approaches. We developed a sensitive sequence alignment pipeline to identify conserved noncoding sequences (CNSs) in the Andropogoneae tribe (multiple crop species descended from a common ancestor ∼18 million years ago). The Andropogoneae share similar physiology while being tremendously genomically diverse, harboring a broad range of ploidy levels, structural variation, and transposons. These contribute to the potential of Andropogoneae as a powerful system for studying CNSs and are factors we leverage to understand the function of maize CNSs. We found that 86% of CNSs were comprised of annotated features, including introns, UTRs, putative cis-regulatory elements, chromatin loop anchors, noncoding RNA (ncRNA) genes, and several transposable element superfamilies. CNSs were enriched in active regions of DNA replication in the early S phase of the mitotic cell cycle and showed different DNA methylation ratios compared to the genome-wide background. More than half of putative cis-regulatory sequences (identified via other methods) overlapped with CNSs detected in this study. Variants in CNSs were associated with gene expression levels, and CNS absence contributed to loss of gene expression. Furthermore, the evolution of CNSs was associated with the functional diversification of duplicated genes in the context of maize subgenomes. Our results provide a quantitative understanding of the molecular processes governing the evolution of CNSs in maize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-genome-research-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://genome.cshlp.org/content/31/7/1245&quot;&gt;Genome Research (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/09/12/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/09/12/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: PAM-less plant genome editing using a CRISPR–SpRY toolbox</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rapid development of the CRISPR–Cas9, –Cas12a and – Cas12b genome editing systems has greatly fuelled basic and translational plant research1–6. DNA targeting by these Cas nucleases is restricted by their preferred protospacer adja- cent motifs (PAMs). The PAM requirement for the most popu- lar Streptococcus pyogenes Cas9 (SpCas9) is NGG (N = A, T, C, G)7, limiting its targeting scope to GC-rich regions. Here, we demonstrate genome editing at relaxed PAM sites in rice (a monocot) and the Dahurian larch (a coniferous tree), using an engineered SpRY Cas9 variant8. Highly efficient targeted mutagenesis can be readily achieved by SpRY at relaxed PAM sites in the Dahurian larch protoplasts and in rice trans- genic lines through non-homologous end joining (NHEJ). Furthermore, an SpRY-based cytosine base editor was devel- oped and demonstrated by directed evolution of new herbicide resistant OsALS alleles in rice. Similarly, a highly active SpRY adenine base editor was developed based on ABE8e (ref. 9) and SpRY-ABE8e was able to target relaxed PAM sites in rice plants, achieving up to 79% editing efficiency with high prod- uct purity. Thus, the SpRY toolbox breaks a PAM restriction barrier in plant genome engineering by enabling DNA editing in a PAM-less fashion. Evidence was also provided for second- ary off-target effects by de novo generated single guide RNAs (sgRNAs) due to SpRY-mediated transfer DNA self-editing, which calls for more sophisticated programmes for designing highly specific sgRNAs when implementing the SpRY genome editing toolbox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-plants-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41477-020-00827-4&quot;&gt;Nature Plants (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/09/06/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/09/06/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: The key role of terminators on the expression and post- transcriptional gene silencing of transgenes</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transgenes have become essential to modern biology, being an important tool in functional genomic studies and also in the development of biotechnological products. One of the major challenges in the generation of transgenic lines concerns the expression of transgenes, which, compared to endogenes, are particularly susceptible to silencing mediated by small RNAs (sRNAs). Several reasons have been put forward to explain why transgenes often trigger the production of sRNAs, such as the high level of expression induced by commonly used strong constitutive promoters, the lack of introns, and features resembling viral and other exogenous sequences. However, the relative contributions of the different genomic elements with respect to protecting genes from the silencing machinery and their molecular mechanisms remain unclear. Here, we present the results of a mutagenesis screen conceived to identify features involved in the protection of endogenes against becoming a template for the production of sRNAs. Interestingly, all of the recovered mutants had alterations in genes with proposed function in transcription termination, suggesting a central role of terminators in this process. Indeed, using a GFP reporter system, we show that, among different genetic elements tested, the terminator sequence had the greatest effect on transgene-derived sRNA accumulation and that a well-defined poly(A) site might be especially important. Finally, we describe an unexpected mechanism, where transgenes containing certain intron/terminator combinations lead to an increase in the production of sRNAs, which appears to interfere with splicing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-the-plant-journal-2020&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/tpj.14907&quot;&gt;The Plant Journal (2020)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/08/29/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/08/29/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: KOBAS-i: intelligent prioritization and exploratory visualization of biological functions for gene enrichment analysis</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gene set enrichment (GSE) analysis plays an essen- tial role in extracting biological insight from genome- scale experiments. ORA (overrepresentation analy- sis), FCS (functional class scoring), and PT (path- way topology) approaches are three generations of GSE methods along the timeline of development. Pre- vious versions of KOBAS provided services based on just the ORA method. Here we presented ver- sion 3.0 of KOBAS, which is named KOBAS-i (short for KOBAS intelligent version). It introduced a novel machine learning-based method we published ear- lier, CGPS, which incorporates seven FCS tools and two PT tools into a single ensemble score and in- telligently prioritizes the relevant biological path- ways. In addition, KOBAS has expanded the down- stream exploratory visualization for selecting and understanding the enriched results. The tool con- structs a novel view of cirFunMap, which presents different enriched terms and their correlations in a landscape. Finally, based on the previous version’s framework, KOBAS increased the number of sup- ported species from 1327 to 5944. For an easier lo- cal run, it also provides a prebuilt Docker image that requires no installation, as a supplementary to the source code version. KOBAS can be freely accessed at http://kobas.cbi.pku.edu.cn, and a mirror site is available at http://bioinfo.org/kobas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nucleic-acids-research-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/nar/article/49/W1/W317/6292104&quot;&gt;Nucleic Acids Research (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/08/01/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/08/01/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: Integrated global analysis reveals a vitamin E- vitamin K1 sub-network, downstream of COLD1, underlying rice chilling tolerance divergence</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rice, a staple food with tropical/subtropical origination, is susceptible to cold stress, one of the major con- straints on its yield and distribution. Asian cultivated rice consists of two subspecies with diverged chilling tolerance to adapt to different environments. The mechanism underlying this divergence remains obscure with a few known factors, including membrane protein CHILLING-TOLERANCE DIVERGENCE 1 (COLD1). Here, we reveal a vitamin E-vitamin K1 sub-network responsible for chilling tolerance divergence through global analyses. Rice genome regions responsible for tolerance divergence are identified with chromosome segment substitution lines (CSSLs). Comparative transcriptomic and metabolomic analysis of chilling- tolerant CSSL4-1 and parent lines uncovered a vitamin E-vitamin K1 sub-network in chloroplast with tocoph- erol (vitamin E) mediating chloroplast-to-nucleus signaling. COLD1, located in the substitution segment in CSSL4-1, is confirmed as its upstream regulator by transgenic material analysis. Our work uncovers a pathway downstream of COLD1, through which rice modulates chilling tolerance for thermal adaptation, with potential utility in crop improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-cell-reports-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cell.com/cell-reports/fulltext/S2211-1247(21)00795-6&quot;&gt;Cell Reports (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/07/26/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/07/26/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Report: The Taxus genome provides insights into paclitaxel biosynthesis</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ancient gymnosperm genus Taxus is the exclusive source of the anticancer drug paclitaxel, yet no reference genome sequences are available for comprehensively elucidating the paclitaxel biosynthesis pathway. We have completed a chromosome-level genome of Taxus chinensis var. mairei with a total length of 10.23 gigabases. Taxus shared an ancestral whole-genome duplication with the coniferophyte lineage and underwent distinct transposon evolution. We discovered a unique physical and functional grouping of CYP725As (cytochrome P450) in the Taxus genome for paclitaxel biosynthesis. We also identified a gene cluster for taxadiene biosynthesis, which was formed mainly by gene duplications. This study will facilitate the elucidation of paclitaxel biosynthesis and unleash the biotechnological potential of Taxus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;source-nature-plants-2021&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41477-021-00963-5&quot;&gt;Nature Plants (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/lab%20meeting/2021/07/18/lab_meeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lab%20meeting/2021/07/18/lab_meeting.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Lab Meeting</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
